<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Eighteen directions for saving conversion unto God by Daniel Burgess ... thus published for the poor.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 30 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30278</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5705</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36045</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">15597720</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 15597720</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104016</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30278)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104016)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1587:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Eighteen directions for saving conversion unto God by Daniel Burgess ... thus published for the poor.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20, [2], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Parkhurst ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisements: p. [1]-[2] of third count.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Devotional exercises.</term>
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Salvation.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104016:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>Eighteen Directions FOR Saving Converſion UNTO GOD. WITH Directions for Daily Holy Living. And Motives, with Directions, unto Religious Diſcourſe; ſuch as tends to promote Converſion and holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. By <hi>Daniel Burgeſs,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel. Thus Publiſhed for the Poor.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chapel. 1691.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104016:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104016:2"/>
                  <p>EIGHTEEN DIRECTIONS FOR Saving Converſion UNTO GOD. By <hi>Daniel Burgeſs,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel. Thus Publiſhed for the Poor.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Park<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> at the lower end of <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi> Chapel. 1691.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104016:3"/>
                  <head>To my Friends in the Counties of <hi>Wilts, Berks, Somerſet, Gloceſter, Oxford, Southampton, Middleſex,</hi> Grace and Peace.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Sirs,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I thankfully</hi> remember all your <hi>old</hi> true Love. And, by your <hi>frequent Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,</hi> I am <hi>comfortably</hi> aſſured of it's <hi>continuance.</hi> Having not any thing bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I <hi>Re-ſalute</hi> you all together, with this <hi>Fragment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I intreat that <hi>your Children</hi> may be exerciſed in Learning to <hi>Underſtand</hi> them and <hi>Recite</hi> them. Eſpecially <hi>thoſe Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whom I Baptized;</hi> and do with an eſpecial Affection remember.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Inſcription</hi> obtains its end; if it certifie you, that You and Yours live in the affectionate memory, of one that ſticks not, <hi>to go out of the common Road</hi> to fetch in one Soul unto Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Fervent Lover and Oratour.</hi> D. Burgeſs.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104016:3"/>
                  <head>Eighteen Directions for Saving Converſion unto God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>D. 1. <hi>BE Men.</hi> Be not content to be <hi>Flies</hi> and <hi>Worms,</hi> or <hi>Dogs</hi> and <hi>Swine</hi> in Men's Shape. You have REA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON; a faculty of Underſtanding and Judging what is <hi>True</hi> and what is <hi>Falſe.</hi> You have a WILL; a freedom of Chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing what you underſtand to be <hi>Good,</hi> and of Refuſing what you think to be <hi>Evil.</hi> You have a CONSCIENCE al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, obliging you always to ACT upon <hi>Choice,</hi> and to CHUSE upon <hi>Judgment.</hi> Be not then, as if you had neither of the three. Be not ſwayed by <hi>brutiſh Senſe;</hi> and acted by <hi>Colours, Smells, Sounds,</hi> and <hi>Taſts,</hi> as if you had been Born in the Field among <hi>Cattel,</hi> and had in you no nobler Principle than they. Riſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104016:4"/> and ſay, each of you; <q rend="inline">From this moment I will uſe my Powers. My Nature is better than Brutes, and my Life ſhall be better. I will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low my exerciſed Reaſon; and ſeek GRACE which is it's Perfection.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Till this be reſolutely ſaid, you have no proper Manhood. No, but are Bruits and worſe, <hi>Morally;</hi> though you are Men, <hi>Naturally,</hi> Pſal. 49.20.</p>
                  <p>D. 2. <hi>Know your Maker.</hi> Endure not to be <hi>Silly Children that know not their own Father.</hi> You know, <hi>you made not your ſelves.</hi> Your <hi>Parents</hi> know little of your <hi>inner</hi> parts; and confeſs that they did not <hi>form</hi> the ſame. You believe your Maker to be one, that was Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf <hi>never made:</hi> But an <hi>Eternal Being,</hi> and the common <hi>Father</hi> and Fountain of all Beings. And by conſequence, of more <hi>Wiſdom, Power</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> than all. And <hi>more worth Knowing,</hi> than all. Riſe then, and ſay every one of you; <q rend="inline">
                        <hi>What good ſhall my Life do me,</hi> if I may not know the <hi>Father</hi> of it? Give me the Knowledge of <hi>my Father,</hi> or <hi>elſe I die.</hi> I will never know reſt, till I underſtand WHO and WHAT He is.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104016:4"/>
                  <p>Go, learn the Sixteen things concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing GOD in the firſt of my Three Queſtions reſolved. Till He be known, nothing can be rightly known. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7, 8.</p>
                  <p>D. 3. <hi>Love your Selves.</hi> Being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from ſo <hi>excellent a Father,</hi> LOVELINESS and LOVE it ſelf; and being ſo <hi>excellent a race of his,</hi> as Men bearing <hi>his Image;</hi> do not make light of your ſelves. <hi>The viſible Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is not,</hi> by millions of times, <hi>worth one of your Souls.</hi> Say then ſtraightway in your Souls, every of you: <q rend="inline">I ſee nothing, but <hi>my God,</hi> better than <hi>my Soul.</hi> Next to <hi>his Glory,</hi> I will therefore make <hi>this Souls good,</hi> my chief <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Care.</hi> If this Soul <hi>be loſt,</hi> it ſhall not be for want of any thing <hi>I can do</hi> to Save it. I will <hi>do</hi> and <hi>ſuffer, work</hi> and <hi>beg, Live</hi> and <hi>Die</hi> for this Soul of mine. For it's <hi>Felicity</hi> in my Maker's <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,</hi> and <hi>Likeneſs.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Until this be ſaid, you do but <hi>Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> you do not <hi>Love</hi> your Selves. No, but, interpretatively, you <hi>Hate</hi> your ſelves. And you <hi>Miſchief</hi> your Selves,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104016:5"/> more than Devils <hi>can</hi> do, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.36.</p>
                  <p>D. 4. <hi>Viſit Heaven and Hell.</hi> You know there is <hi>another World;</hi> (none of you all pretend <hi>to be ſure,</hi> that there is <hi>not</hi> another.) If there be another, confine not your Acquaintance unto this. <hi>Heathens, Turks,</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves believe another World: And ſay it is a <hi>Bigger</hi> than this, and an <hi>Ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting</hi> one. And one, whoſe <hi>Pleaſures</hi> exceed thoſe of this lower Worlds, as much as the Light of the Sun ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth the Gloworm's. Whoſe <hi>Pains</hi> and <hi>Torments</hi> alſo be ſuch, that the <hi>worſt Torments</hi> here wou'd be <hi>very Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhments</hi> unto the tormented there. Let every one then ſay, <q rend="inline">I will as daily <hi>think of</hi> the next World, as I <hi>breath in</hi> this. And <hi>Fear</hi> the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of that World, more than the pains of this. And <hi>Deſire and ſeek</hi> the Pleaſures of that World, more than all of this.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Before this Practice, you do not <hi>ſee afar off,</hi> but <hi>are blind.</hi> You live in this World, as <hi>Spiders in their Webs;</hi> careleſs and thoughtleſs of the Beeſom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104016:5"/> of deſtruction. And as <hi>Serpents in the Duſt,</hi> regardleſs of the glory of higher Regions, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.18.</p>
                  <p>D. 5. <hi>Call Earth your Purgatory.</hi> Your <hi>Time here,</hi> is, all of it, given you on <hi>Tryal;</hi> and for <hi>Preparation</hi> for your Eternal State. Your <hi>Maker</hi> is Holy; his <hi>Heaven</hi> is Pure; <hi>All that enter it</hi> muſt be Purified; <hi>their Time</hi> is allowed them for Purification. As they <hi>are Purified</hi> or <hi>not Purified</hi> here on Earth, they are <hi>taken into</hi> Heaven or <hi>excluded.</hi> No other <hi>Place</hi> of Purifying, or <hi>Time,</hi> is ſet by God. Say then, Reader, ſay often unto thy ſelf; <q rend="inline">My <hi>time</hi> is my <hi>tryal for Eternity;</hi> I am <hi>here, on my good behaviour;</hi> as I <hi>Live</hi> here, I <hi>Speed</hi> for ever. After my death God will neither hold me on tryal in that World, nor ſend me back again, and try me in this. If I am Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied I muſt be Purified; and if Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, it muſt be now. My Motto ſhall be NOW or NEVER, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.15, 16. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9, 10.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 6. <hi>Believe and ſearch God's Word.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the H. <hi>Scripture</hi> ſo to be. It is, in a
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104016:6"/> manner, as plain that the <hi>Scripture</hi> is his <hi>Word,</hi> as that the <hi>World</hi> is his <hi>Work.</hi> Men could no more invent ſuch a <hi>Bible,</hi> than they could make ſuch a <hi>World.</hi> (Read Dr. <hi>Manton,</hi> Dr <hi>Bates,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> hereof, you ſhall ſay ſo.) As ſure as there is a God, his Will muſt be Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed; but if it be not Revealed in the H. Scripture, where is it Revealed? And what is there in the Scripture but is like Him, and ſpeaks it ſelf His? And if His it be, how <hi>Continually, Aw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,</hi> and <hi>Affectionately</hi> ſhould it be ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died? <hi>Rather than neglect it, I would burn all my other Books, and read the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture by the light of them.</hi> Say thou that readeſt this; upon due conſideration ſay thou; <q rend="inline">If I had a thouſand Souls, I would venture them all upon the truth of theſe H. Scriptures. I reſolve to Live and Die by them. And I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage my ſelf here, in preſence of their bleſſed Author, that I will as daily read this his Word, as I eat his Bread, <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.39. <hi>Col.</hi> 3.16. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.97.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 7. <hi>Eſteem Godlineſs God-likeneſs.</hi> You know little of God's Word till
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104016:6"/> you do ſo. It's true, <hi>Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> and the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>Lyar from the beginning,</hi> do give Godlineſs another report. Even a very black Character. They repreſent it as <hi>a very Hell upon Earth.</hi> But God's Word <hi>ſays</hi> the clean contrary; as his Children alſo <hi>feel</hi> the clean contrary. Godlineſs, all agree, is nothing but Imitating, and Obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God. Now, to <hi>Imitate him</hi> (in Wiſdom, Truth, and Goodneſs,) can be nothing but Beauty and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and Benefit and Honour. And to <hi>Obey him,</hi> is no other. Being He is <hi>too Great,</hi> to have his ſervice any diſparagement unto Angels; and <hi>too Good,</hi> to let it go unrewarded unto Men. Nor puts He <hi>his Children on Earth</hi> upon any thing, but what He put <hi>his Son in Heaven</hi> upon, whiles he was here. Will He have us <hi>Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer,</hi> as well as <hi>Labour</hi> for him? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide that, <hi>we may thank our Sin for it;</hi> let us conſider, <hi>The Natural Son of God</hi> ſuffered the <hi>Curſe of the Law;</hi> the <hi>Adopted Children of God</hi> ſuffer nothing but the <hi>Chaſtiſements of Grace.</hi> He was <hi>made perfect by vaſtly greater Sufferings.</hi> Add hereto; what are <hi>light Sufferings</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104016:7"/> and <hi>but for a moment,</hi> for an <hi>exceeding great</hi> Crown and <hi>Eternal?</hi> And think too; Can the Devil name <hi>any thing in Holineſs,</hi> ſo hard as we can prove <hi>all things in Sin</hi> to be? And, <hi>all places in Hell</hi> to be? Love is all Religion, and all Pleaſure is Love. <hi>God only,</hi> is more bleſſed than <hi>a Man Godly.</hi> Conclude thou thus, <hi>Reader,</hi> and ſay; <q rend="inline">Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth will I ſeek <hi>Fiſh</hi> in the <hi>Air</hi> and <hi>Fowls</hi> in the <hi>Sea,</hi> as ſoon as ſeek <hi>Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> or <hi>Honour</hi> any where but in <hi>Godlineſs. Pſal.</hi> 119.92. <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 8. <hi>Beware of the Mill and the Circle.</hi> Of the <hi>Mill</hi> of worldly <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> and of the <hi>Circle</hi> of Senſual <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> They be the <hi>Traps</hi> that take moſt Souls; and are the <hi>Death</hi> of all that they take. The <hi>Mill</hi> doth ſtore Hell with you <hi>poor Tenants,</hi> and the <hi>Circle</hi> ſtores it with your <hi>Rich Landlords.</hi> You have but <hi>one Soul,</hi> and can Love beſt but <hi>one thing;</hi> if the Worlds Profits or Pleaſures get the Throne of your one Soul, you have no other for God; and <hi>He will ſit no where but on the Throne,</hi> and in your BEST Love. Nor have you but <hi>one
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104016:7"/> Life-time</hi> for working out your Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. If this one be eat up by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Vulturs, your Salvation is loſt. Say then <hi>Reader,</hi> if thou careſt to be ſaved; <q rend="inline">Heart and Life-Religion, ſhall be my prime <hi>Mill</hi> and <hi>Circle;</hi> my chief <hi>Buſineſs</hi> and <hi>Pleaſure.</hi> World<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ones will follow me; but I will follow theſe. And of all things in the World I will keep the Throne of my Heart from Worldly Buſineſs and Pleaſures. The Bloodieſt <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants</hi> and <hi>Butchers</hi> of Humane Souls, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.15, 16, 17. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.29, 30, 31.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 9. <hi>Keep out of Peſt-houſes.</hi> Out of the Company of <hi rend="sup">1</hi> Men <hi>falſely ſo called;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">2</hi> Men, <hi>that know not their God;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">3</hi> Men <hi>that love death, and wrong their own Souls;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">4</hi> Men, <hi>that look not into any World but this;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">5</hi> Men, <hi>that mind not Times End and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">6</hi> Men, <hi>that value Bibles no more than</hi> Plutarch<hi>'s Morals;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">7</hi> Men, <hi>that fancy God's Service wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Bondany;</hi> 
                     <hi rend="sup">8</hi> Men, like Bees, either <hi>buſie in</hi> gathering <hi>Honey</hi> or Drowned in it. <hi>Wiſdom</hi> hath ſaid it, <hi>Juſtice</hi> hath ordered it, and <hi>Goodneſs</hi> hath warned
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104016:8"/> you of it. <hi>A Companion of Fools ſhall be deſtroyed.</hi> Come not <hi>of choice</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, near unto their Doors. The choice of <hi>Company,</hi> is in a great degree the choice of your <hi>State;</hi> of Sin and Miſery, or of Grace and Salvation, I mean. Say, if thou <hi>art</hi> Wiſe, or if thou ever wouldſt be Wiſe; ſay and hold; <q rend="inline">I will henceforth chuſe to aſſociate with <hi>Frogs and Toads,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than with <hi>Gods Enemies.</hi> I will have no <hi>Boſom Friend</hi> that hath not ſome <hi>Holineſs to the Lord wrote on his Forehead,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.2. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.21.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 10. <hi>Have a care of your Eyes.</hi> In <hi>Nature</hi> you may be Blind, and Live; in <hi>Grace</hi> you cannot. <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Error</hi> Damn Souls, as ſurely as Sins againſt Light and Knowledge. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially where there is plenty of means of Knowledge. <hi>Heaven</hi>'s a far Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey; <hi>Holineſs</hi> is a narrow way to it; And is a <hi>Blind Man</hi> like to hit it, do you think? Beſides, <hi>Darkneſs</hi> is that whereof <hi>Satan is the Prince</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>orance is called the <hi>Power of the Devil;</hi> and Chriſt is ſaid to be coming to take
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104016:8"/> vengeance of all that KNOW NOT God, and that (do not more than Know,) that OBEY not the (whole) GOSPEL. Reader, go beg Gods Eye-ſalve, ſay preſently; <q rend="inline">Grace is called Light, and Glory is called Light; I will no more endure this dark Heart of mine. I will never be quiet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til I get to underſtand all the Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental TRUTHS, GRACES, and DUTIES of Chriſtianity.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>For thy Life get underſtanding of the <hi>Aſſemblies Catechiſm.</hi> Of the <hi>Summaries of Truths</hi> in my Three Queſtions reſolved, <hi>&amp;c. Prov.</hi> 4.5, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.4. The <hi>Grand Charter Iſſued out and Granted by Jeſus Chriſt</hi> for the Plantation of the Chriſtian Faith in all Nations. By <hi>George Lawſon,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor of <hi>More</hi> in the County of <hi>Salop.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 11. <hi>Highly prize Sunſhine and Thunder.</hi> Plain and clear, Rouzing and piercing Sermons. How dull are your Heads? What can <hi>Benefit</hi> you, that doth not <hi>Inform</hi> you? And what can <hi>Inform</hi> you that is not as <hi>plain as the Sun?</hi> Your Hearts be likewiſe cold and frozen deſperately. What beſides
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:104016:9"/> 
                     <hi>Thunder-bolts</hi> can break 'em? What beſides <hi>Flaſhes of Fire</hi> can thaw them? Believe it, <hi>dark and dull Preachers</hi> be fearful <hi>Judgments and Curſes to ſuch as I ſuppoſe you. Ignorance,</hi> makes ſome Preachers dark; <hi>Pride,</hi> maketh others; but <hi>Sin</hi> makes both; and both do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Sin. Say thus, thou that valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt thy Soul; <q rend="inline">I will pray God to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect me to a Miniſtry both <hi>Shining</hi> and <hi>Burning:</hi> Plain for my <hi>dull Mind,</hi> Powerful for my <hi>rocky Heart.</hi> Clear to inform my <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> and as Cutting and Searching to excite me <hi>Affection, Iſa.</hi> 58.1. <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 6.5.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 12. <hi>Beg of God Golden Snuffers.</hi> We do all <hi>need</hi> Reprovers. And ſo <hi>peeviſh</hi> we, all, are, that unleſs they be <hi>excellent</hi> ones; very <hi>Compaſſionate</hi> and very <hi>Diſcreet,</hi> and very <hi>Innocent</hi> themſelves; we cannot bear them when they reprove us. We receive no good from the <hi>Snuffers,</hi> except they be of <hi>pure Gold;</hi> it is ſeldom that we ever do. Great need therefore there is, that thou Prayeſt the <hi>Over-ruler of all things,</hi> to beſtow upon thee ſome <hi>Righteous ones</hi> to <hi>ſmite</hi> thee. Some
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104016:9"/> 
                     <hi>Skilful</hi> Friends, and <hi>Faithful,</hi> and of <hi>excellent Holineſs</hi> to tell thee ever and anon of thy Miſcarriages. Such as thy <hi>Miniſter</hi> never hears of; and can but <hi>generally</hi> reprove. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141.5. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.14. <hi>Exod.</hi> 37.23.</p>
                  <p>D. 13. <hi>Suppoſe the worſt of your Selves.</hi> Your own Hearts will be forward to Preſume <hi>all is well</hi> quickly; and that <hi>God and you are Reconciled.</hi> Satan alſo ſtill puſhes on toward preſumption. Towards Hope without <hi>any</hi> ground for it: Or, at leaſt, without <hi>juſt</hi> ground for it. But fair and ſoft, goes beſt and fartheſt. Think thus; if you are indeed Reconciled, your Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your ſelf will not <hi>break;</hi> no, but <hi>Clear</hi> and <hi>Strengthen</hi> the Reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation; and bring you in abundance of comfort. But if you are <hi>not Recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled</hi> to God, you <hi>never can be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led until you know your want of it.</hi> And Examination, is Gods appointed way for your Knowledge. Do not ſay, <hi>But this Knowledge will ſcare us.</hi> For, I pray, what will Hell do? What! <hi>Will you not</hi> bear the <hi>Judgment Seat of your own Conſciences?</hi> Whether you
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104016:10"/> will or no, you ſhall bear God's <hi>grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Judgment Seat.</hi> Go reſolve then, and ſay thou; <q rend="inline">Never will I be <hi>high-minded;</hi> but <hi>Fear.</hi> I will maintain a <hi>godly Jealouſie</hi> of my Self and my State. Daily will I <hi>Examine,</hi> and pray God to Examine, my <hi>Heart;</hi> and try my <hi>Ways.</hi> I will Conſult my <hi>God,</hi> my <hi>Heart,</hi> my <hi>Miniſter</hi> and my <hi>Friends,</hi> about the grounds of my Hopes, and Comforts, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.27. <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.17.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 14. <hi>Sleep not on the top of a Maſt.</hi> Do not <hi>Delay</hi> to mend your Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, while it is <hi>apparently</hi> dangerous. He that is <hi>on the Ladder,</hi> is <hi>near to Execution;</hi> and <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nregenerate</hi> men be all <hi>on the Ladder.</hi> Delay is not for them; every breath, for ought they know, is their Laſt. <hi>(See my Sermon againſt Delay in the Morning Lectures.)</hi> Say to thy Soul, as the <hi>Angel</hi> to <hi>Lot;</hi> 
                     <q rend="inline">
                        <hi>Ariſe, leſt thou be conſumed; Eſcape for thy Life,</hi> NEITHER STAY THOU. <hi>Eſcape, leſt thou be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed.</hi> If thou doſt not flee, wrath will come; and thou wilt not be able to flee from it, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.1.</q>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104016:10"/> 
                     <hi>Now,</hi> in days of <hi>Youth.</hi> No <hi>Delay,</hi> in <hi>Youth</hi> it ſelf, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</p>
                  <p>D. 15. <hi>Let thy Sins be but Falls, and not Leaps.</hi> Though, after all, thou doeſt the <hi>Evil that thou wouldſt not do;</hi> ſee that thou doeſt not one more, than what is againſt thy will. Thou <hi>falleſt</hi> into Sin, when for want of ſtrength thou committeſt it: Thou <hi>leapeſt</hi> into it when thou committeſt it with conſent, of choice, and for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry pleaſure. True, the wages of all ſin, is DEATH; yet the former is a <hi>Gnat,</hi> and the latter a <hi>Camel.</hi> So wide is the difference. And the Goſpel is plain; <hi>Lambs</hi> fall into the mire, but they are <hi>Swine</hi> that leap into, and wallow in it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.13. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.15, 16, 17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26.</p>
                  <p>D. 16. <hi>Row againſt the ſtream.</hi> The World wonderfully miſtakes CAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NOT for WILL-NOT. Beware you of it; for it may ſoon become fatal. Uſe your ſelves unto this Language: <q rend="inline">Here is a Duty, againſt which my mind is full of carnal Objections; and my Will full of like Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:104016:11"/> But againſt both, <hi>I will Fight; God help me by his Grace to Conquer.</hi> The Duty goes againſt me, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs; but I, for God, will go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Self. I am aſham'd that I cannot do it more Freely, but I will go force my ſelf to perform it. Though I cannot Cheerfully, I will Mournfully perform it. Men are ſometimes bid to Eat for a Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach; I will go Obey to get a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Heart to Obey with. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64 7. God rewards Duty with Duty, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.55, 56.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 17. <hi>Flee from Popery.</hi> When you have gone thus far, admit no conceit of <hi>Merit</hi> in it. Dream not that <hi>your own ſtrength</hi> brought you ſo far, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Without the <hi>Grace</hi> of Chriſt, nothing <hi>can be done.</hi> And it muſt be for his <hi>alone Merit,</hi> that all <hi>is accepted,</hi> when it is done. Every one of your <hi>good Thoughts,</hi> are the works of his <hi>Spirit.</hi> And every <hi>kind look of God up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you,</hi> is the purchaſe of his <hi>Blood.</hi> You muſt never expect to <hi>Repent, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,</hi> or <hi>Obey,</hi> but by his <hi>Strength.</hi> And when you do, you muſt never
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104016:11"/> look for <hi>acceptance</hi> with God but up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Merit of his <hi>Obedience. Rom.</hi> 5.18, 19. <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.4. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.30. <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.17. <hi>NB.</hi> 1. Chriſt ſatisfied God offended with us; He payed what we Owed, and could not pay. 2. God Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted what Chriſt performed, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed on our behalf. 3. Believers enjoy the Fruits of Chriſts Perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance being ſo Accepted. 4. And, therefore muſt not Believe or Obey for thoſe Ends for which Chriſt did Obey; I mean, to Satisfie Gods Juſtice, and to Merit his Mercy.</p>
                  <p>D. 18. Finally and Principally; <hi>Take no reſt, and give God none; till, through his Grace, you diſcern your ſelves to have riſen up, orderly, theſe ſeven Steps.</hi> By theſe he leads every one of his Choſen, unto the Glory prepared for them. Nor are you to preach peace unto your Souls till they have aſcended them all.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. CONVICTION. Or a thorough Perſwaſion of the <hi>Sinfulneſs, Miſerable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> but <hi>Changeableneſs</hi> of your Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. (See Twelve neceſſary Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions in <hi>my Call unto Sinners.</hi>) John 16.8.</p>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:104016:12"/>
                  <p n="2">2. CONSIDERATION. Or <hi>Seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, Much,</hi> and <hi>Frequent</hi> Meditation of the things whereof you are Convinced in your Hearts, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.59.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. CONTRITION. Or <hi>Fear,</hi> and <hi>Grief,</hi> and <hi>Shame</hi> and <hi>Hatred</hi> of Sin, wrought by the Conſideration aforeſaid, as the means thereof. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51.17.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. CONSULTATION. Or En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry and Taking Counſel of <hi>God,</hi> and of <hi>his Servants,</hi> what to do for Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Union unto Chriſt and Saving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in him. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. ACCEPTATION. To wit of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt to be your <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Prieſt, King,</hi> and <hi>Pattern</hi> or <hi>Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar.</hi> Intelligent and Sincere CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SENT to his being all four, unto and for you. <hi>John</hi> 1.12.</p>
                  <p n="6">6. DEDICATION. Or, Solemn Compleating of that ſaid Acceptation, by <hi>Purpoſe, Promiſe,</hi> and <hi>Vows</hi> to <hi>Learn</hi> 2of Chriſt, to <hi>Truſt</hi> in him, to <hi>Obey</hi> him, to <hi>Imitate</hi> him. And this, both by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> and <hi>Spiritual,</hi> and <hi>Outward</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental</hi> Covenanting, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 44.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.8. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.27. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.16, 17.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. CONVERSATION. Or, a Life
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104016:12"/> expreſſive of all aforeſaid. A Life apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſignifying that the Soul has been <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced, Conſiderate, Contrite, Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, Acceptive of Chriſt, Dedicative</hi> of it ſelf unto Chriſt. A Life of <hi>endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> though <hi>not attained,</hi> Perfection. <hi>Col.</hi> 2.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50 21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.18, 19. Mark here, the AS YE HAVE, and the SO NOW YIELD; and obſerve well the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of it. <hi>We ſhould SO ſerve God and Holineſs in our Regenerate State, AS we did ſerve Sin and Satan in our <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate State.</hi> Even SO,
<list>
                        <item>1. So <hi>Readily</hi> and Freely.</item>
                        <item>2. So <hi>Reſolutely</hi> and Invincibly.</item>
                        <item>3. So <hi>Carefully</hi> and Studiouſly.</item>
                        <item>4. So <hi>Painfully</hi> and Induſtriouſly.</item>
                        <item>5. So <hi>Pleaſantly</hi> and Delightfully.</item>
                        <item>6. So <hi>Perpetually</hi> and Inceſſantly.</item>
                        <item>7. So <hi>Progreſſively</hi> and Proficiently.</item>
                        <item>8. So <hi>Perſwaſively of others,</hi> and with Zeal provoking many.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>NATURE will not let a <hi>Man</hi> live, without <hi>ſome</hi> Service of God. And GRACE will not let a Chriſtian live, without <hi>ſuch Service as this,</hi> Performed, or at leaſt Endeavoured.</p>
                  <p>Go, Reader, and ſay to this effect; <q rend="inline">Morning, Noon, and Night, <hi>I will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:104016:13"/> be Catechiſing</hi> my Soul about theſe ſeven things. Yea, and <hi>I will deſire my Paſtor to Catechiſe me concerning them.</hi> And till I have ALL, I will account my ſelf NOTHING; yea WORSE than Nothing.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>May <hi>every Peruſer,</hi> be a <hi>Practiſer</hi> of theſe Directions! May <hi>all my Imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections</hi> in them, be <hi>forgiven,</hi> in the Blood of my Redeemer, by my graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous God! May <hi>my more Judicious Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren</hi> (more able in Speaking, and more able in Writing,) be drawn to publiſh their <hi>more Elaborate Directions,</hi> by the good Succeſs of <hi>theſe ſo haſtily thrown to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether!</hi> May theſe Lines <hi>Live,</hi> when I am <hi>Dead;</hi> and <hi>Speak,</hi> when <hi>my Breath is Stopt;</hi> and (in the mean time) may they <hi>Preach unto Thouſands,</hi> of whom I can <hi>never ſee the Faces,</hi> till the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection! <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="publishers_advertisement">
                  <pb facs="tcp:104016:13"/>
                  <head>Books Printed for, and Sold by <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers Chapel.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Call to Sinners, ſuch as are under Sentence of Death, and ſuch as are under any Proſpect of it: from the Long-ſuffering and Gracious, but moſt Righteous God.</p>
                  <p>Three Queſtions reſolved briefly and plainly, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) What Conceptions ought we to have of the bleſſed God? (2.) What are thoſe Truths, whereof the Knowledge appeareth moſt indiſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly neceſſary unto our Salvation; and (therefore) to be firſt and moſt learnt by us? (3.) What is the change wrought in a Man by God's H. Spirit, before he can ſafely conclude himſelf paſs'd from Death to Life? Being the Summ of three Sermons.</p>
                  <p>A ſeaſonable Queſtion plainly reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: <hi>viz.</hi> What are we to judge of their Spiritual Eſtate, who neglect the Lord's Supper? And, What is that diſcerning of the Lord's Body in it, without which Men do eat and drink their own Dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation?</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:104016:14"/>
                  <p>Mans whole Duty, and Gods won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful Intreaty of him thereunto. Set forth from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. and publiſhed at the Requeſt of ſome Hearers.</p>
                  <p>Advice to Parents and Children. The Sum of a few Sermons, Contracted, and Publiſhed at the Requeſt of many Pious Hearers.</p>
                  <p>Chriſtian Commemoration, and Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of Saints Departed; Explicated, and Preſſed from <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7. occaſion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Deceaſe of the Reverend Mr. <hi>Henry Hurſt,</hi> Lately Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>London.</hi> All Six by <hi>Daniel Burgeſs</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="tract">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104016:14"/>
                  <head>Directions for Daily Holy Living, by D. <hi>Burgeſs</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</head>
                  <p>D. 1. <hi>LImit your ſleeping hours.</hi> Let them not be as many as brutiſh <hi>Senſe</hi> demandeth. Let <hi>Reaſon</hi> fit their number to your Health and Labour. Your <hi>Motion</hi> is not by the Rule of Religion, if your <hi>Reſt</hi> be not ſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 139.18. <hi>I awake, that I may be ſtill with thee.</hi> So, ſome Learned read it.</p>
                  <p>D. 2. <hi>Conſecrate your waking thoughts.</hi> Let your God have thoſe firſt Fruits. He always Loved the firſt of all things. The <hi>firſt Fruits,</hi> and <hi>firſt Born,</hi> under the Law, were his. Preſent Him with theſe, every morning. Thoughts are inward Speeches. Let God hear Himſelf firſt ſpoken of by you, ſtill. It will argue that He <hi>is</hi> your Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, and it will make Him <hi>more</hi> ſo Love makes Thoughtful; and Thoughtfulneſs makes Love. A Potter is known by his Veſſels, and a Heart by its Thoughts; and of all Thoughts, by its firſt in the morning, and laſt at night. <hi>My voice ſhalt thou hear
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:104016:15"/> in the morning, O Lord!</hi> Pſal. 5.3.</p>
                  <p>D. 3. <hi>Regulate your Bodily Dreſſes.</hi> Long Dreſſes bewray large Conſciences, if no worſe. He that duly prefers his Soul above his Body, would rather go like the wild <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> than dreſs like ſome <hi>Londoners.</hi> The Hebrew word <hi>Beged,</hi> ſignifies <hi>Cloathing</hi> and <hi>Covenant-breaking.</hi> God ſeems to have taught thereby, that the Cloaths on our backs ſhould humble us for the ſin of our firſt Parents and Perſons. But if they do not ſo; and if outward Adorning be that which employs our early hours, and ſevere thoughts, it will be dearly paid for in our dying hours, with tormenting thoughts, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.3. <hi>Whoſe adorning let it not be that outward adorning.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 4. <hi>Time well your Cloſet and Family Worſhip.</hi> They be not the ſame things <hi>in</hi> ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and <hi>out</hi> of ſeaſon. Let the <hi>Word</hi> be read; one verſe rather than none; and Prayer be made; the ſhorteſt, rather than none; both by your ſelves alone, and with your Families. If it may be, worſhip firſt by your ſelves. But, needleſly tie not your ſelves, being God hath not bound you unto ſuch and ſuch hours. Still do, as you verily think is moſt for Edification, <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Enter into thy cloſet, and when thou haſt ſhut the door, pray to thy Father.</hi> Joſh. 24.15. <hi>As for
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:104016:15"/> me and my Houſe, we will ſerve the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 5. <hi>Sanctifie your worldly Buſineſs.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is your buſineſs but that which God your Maſter ſets you about. Dare not then do any thing, but that whereto you can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>title Him. Nor dare you to do it for any other chief end, but to pleaſe Him. When you do WHAT He ſets you, and ſupremely BECAUSE He ſets it, and wills that you do it; knowing and hoping for his Dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in it, and Bleſſing of it; you then ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctifie it: Then HOLINESS TO THE LORD is written upon it, whatever it be, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31. <hi>Whether ye Eat or Drink, or WHATSOEVER ye do, do all to the glory of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 6. <hi>Moderate your Pains in your Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings.</hi> Pains muſt be; Sweat, is required. But by <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion</hi> they muſt be meaſured. God's Laws be all Juſt and Good. <hi>Drones</hi> that will not work muſt not eat. He that is a <hi>ſluggard in his work,</hi> is branded as <hi>Brother of the Prodigal waſter, Prov.</hi> 18.9. <hi>Drudges,</hi> of whoſe Labour there is no end, and who bereave their Souls of good; who uſe themſelves worſe than God allows Oxen to be uſed; <hi>Treading out the Corn, and muzzling themſelves;</hi> theſe are branded by the Spirit of God, as incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104016:16"/> abſurd, and ſelf-deſtroying fools, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Diligent hands</hi> have the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of being made <hi>rich:</hi> That is, Hands that be neither <hi>Drones</hi> nor <hi>Drudges,</hi> Prov. 10.4. <hi>The hand of the diligent maketh rich.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 7. <hi>Strengthen your guards againſt your ſtrongeſt Enemies.</hi> Sin, is our Enemy; even <hi>One</hi> and <hi>All.</hi> God <hi>hates</hi> nothing but ſin; and man can be <hi>hurt</hi> by nothing but ſin. Sin's name is <hi>Legion;</hi> for it is <hi>many.</hi> And of the <hi>many,</hi> there is ſome <hi>one</hi> or other in every man, that <hi>has more power</hi> than all the reſt. That <hi>gives ſtrength</hi> unto all the reſt. And, being mortified, all the reſt are mortified. There be alſo beſide that KING-ſin in the Souls, ſome kind of PEER-ſins, which, of all, next unto the KING-ſin, are by far the moſt dangerous. The KING-ſin is (alway or moſtly) your <hi>Temperamental</hi> ſin; the ſin of your Conſtitution. The PEER-ſins, be the <hi>Radical ones,</hi> of Senſuality, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief, Hypocriſie; and the <hi>way-laying ones,</hi> whereunto Temptations will every day meet us in our Company and Buſineſs. You can never have any but a falſe Peace, till you can ſay, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.23. <hi>I am upright before the Lord; I keep my ſelf from my own iniquity.</hi> Doctor <hi>Bates,</hi> his little Book upon that Text is a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:104016:16"/> 
                     <hi>Light</hi> and a <hi>Lamp,</hi> a <hi>Rod</hi> and a <hi>Staff.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 8. <hi>Govern your Thoughts and your Words.</hi> Let not your <hi>Minds</hi> or <hi>Tongues</hi> be unbridled, and run whither they will. You are in your Shops and your Buſineſs very often, alone; <hi>Reverence your Conſcience,</hi> and dare not in the preſence of God's Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent to ſuffer a ſinful or uſeleſs ſelf-diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. But talk with your ſelves of <hi>great and good Subjects,</hi> and with deſigns of <hi>great and good Effects</hi> upon your hearts by them. When you are in company, conſider your Tongue's need of Government: All its words be <hi>Meat</hi> or <hi>Poiſon</hi> to your Hearers, and your ſelves: They do ſtill holily make for <hi>Edification,</hi> or ſubſerviently for <hi>Recrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or contrarily for <hi>Corruption,</hi> Prov. 24.9. <hi>The THOUGHT of fooliſhneſs is ſin,</hi> Mat. 12.36. <hi>Of every idle WORD that men ſhall ſpeak, they ſhall give account in the day of Judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 9. <hi>Preſerve the Prerogative of your King.</hi> I mean, of your Love. Your Love of God, of Angels, of Men: That is your Principal Grace; your Prince. <hi>Keep that Prince on horſe-back;</hi> let that ride, and reign, and rule you in all you do. Let not any thing lower, move and ſway you more, in any of your ways. Remember
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:104016:17"/> ſtill, it is Love that is the higheſt improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our <hi>Faculties,</hi> the End of all other <hi>Graces,</hi> the Excellency in all other <hi>Graces.</hi> For this is the <hi>Word</hi> of God given, for this is the <hi>Spirit</hi> given, for this was his <hi>Son</hi> given, that we might Love! Never pleaſe your ſelves therefore with any Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or any external Duty, without Love, internal Love, animating, enlivening, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.10. <hi>Love is the fulfilling of the Law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 10. <hi>Value highly your Time.</hi> Do ſo really, in more than empty pretence. And do ſo apparently alſo. Apparently unto your own Conſcience, Family, Friends, Neighbours. Tell all in the Language of Practice, you account them as the worſt of Thieves, who rob you of your Time. Say as Mr. <hi>Fowler, My Time and Strength is God's, and he ſhall have it.</hi> And as Mr. <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin, Chriſt ſhall not find me idle.</hi> Eſteem every <hi>ſmall moity</hi> of Time, as you do of Gold. Expend <hi>none at all,</hi> of it, but in mowing and whetting your Sythe; in ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Duty, and neceſſary Recreation. Buy <hi>a great deal of it;</hi> I mean, part with much vain pleaſure, ſecular profit, fools favour and kindneſs, and good men's too ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, to ſave your Time. To ſave it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:104016:17"/> from doing of <hi>evil,</hi> and from doing of <hi>leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer good,</hi> when you may do <hi>greater.</hi> That is indeed, as we are bid, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.16. <hi>To Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem the Time.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 11. <hi>Exerciſe Chriſtian Temperance in all your Meals. Brutes,</hi> are more temperate in uſe of food, than many men. And, may I not ſay, that ſome <hi>unregenerate men</hi> are more temperate, than here and there a well reputed Chriſtian appears? This is a ſhame. Exceſs in Meat and Drink, is not the leaſt fruitful ſin againſt Body or Soul. To be abſtemious and ſparing for Health's ſake, is to be as wiſe as Brute creatures, and ſome men graceleſs. Abſtinence, for Conſcience ſake; of love to God and Chriſt, to our own Souls and others; of faithfulneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to our Baptiſmal Engagement; this is Chriſtian Temperance, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.49. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold this was the ſin of</hi> Sodom, <hi>Pride, FUL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NESS of BREAD, and abundance of IDLENESS was in her.</hi> Sin came in by eating; remember then <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.2. <hi>Put a knife to thy throat, if thou be a man given to Appetite.</hi> And, <hi>Be not deſirous of Dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; for they are deceitful meat,</hi> Rom. 8.13. <hi>If ye live after the fleſh, ye ſhall die.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 12. <hi>Haſten your Recoveries out of your wilful ſins.</hi> For, ſins of <hi>unavoidable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmity,</hi>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:104016:18"/> God threatens not <hi>Eternal</hi> Plagues, or <hi>Temporal</hi> Judgments on you. Sincere and conſtant Humiliation for them, is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>neceſſary</hi> and <hi>natural,</hi> to Lovers of God and Chriſt. But ſins that are <hi>not of common and inſuperable Infirmity,</hi> they make fearful breaches of your Peace with God, and ſore wounds in your Souls. They ſadly leſſen God's Love of Complacence in you, and your Love and all graces towards God. When you fall into theſe, dare not to lie one minute in them; <hi>Lament</hi> them preſently; <hi>Confeſs</hi> them preſently to God, and (if need be) unto man alſo. Repent, rent your hearts <hi>for them,</hi> and rent them alſo <hi>from them,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay. Cry for the Balm of Chriſt's Blood to be preſently dropt into your wounds; and for the clean Water of his Spirit to be preſently poured on you. Cry mightily for <hi>Pardon</hi> of them, and <hi>Aſſiſtance</hi> againſt them. Every minutes delay may coſt you ſo many days, weeks and months dolor and anguiſh. Choſen delays may make ſo many <hi>Spira</hi>'s of you, for ought I know, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.3. <hi>While I kept ſilence, i. e.</hi> would not confeſs my ſin, <hi>my bones waxed old, i. e.</hi> I ſuffered dearly.</p>
                  <p>D. 13. <hi>Examine ſtrictly your Relative Duty.</hi> Often ſay, What <hi>Subject</hi> am I? What
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:104016:18"/> 
                     <hi>Fellow-Subject?</hi> What <hi>Obſerver of Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Miniſters?</hi> What <hi>Friend</hi> am I? <hi>How do I carry it toward my Enemies?</hi> For a Chriſtian can be no one's Enemy! as far as he is a Chriſtian, he cannot. What <hi>Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band</hi> or <hi>Wife</hi> am I? What <hi>Parent</hi> or <hi>Child</hi> am I? What <hi>Maſter</hi> or <hi>Servant</hi> am I? What <hi>Superior,</hi> what <hi>Inferior,</hi> what <hi>Equal</hi> am I? Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity or Hypocriſie, is, for the moſt part ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeen in theſe things, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.11. <hi>What manner of perſons ought ye to be in all holy Converſations and Godlineſſes?</hi> Pſal. 119.6. <hi>Then ſhall I not be aſhamed, when I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect unto all thy Commandments.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 14. <hi>Repeat every Evening your double uſe of the WORD and PRAYER.</hi> I mean, in your Cloſet and Family. Dare not for the gain of a Kingdom to omit it, of choice. Nor to perform it without greateſt Seriouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Willingneſs &amp; Thankfulneſs, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 55.17. <hi>Evening and Morning, and at Noon, will I pray and cry aloud, and he ſhall hear my voice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 15. <hi>Repair every days Loſſes, and be chary of every days Gains.</hi> I mean your <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> ones. The Womb of ſome days doth bring you forth huge <hi>Hindrances</hi> of Duty to God, to your ſelves, and to your Families. III <hi>Perſons</hi> or <hi>Things</hi> obſtruct your Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. When they do ſo, conſider and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:104016:19"/> conſult, and ſtrain hard to make it up the next day. Read, Pray, Meditate, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo much the more. Another day brings forth huge <hi>Helps.</hi> A <hi>Lecture,</hi> a <hi>Faſt,</hi> or Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Thankſgiving,</hi> a <hi>Funeral Sermon,</hi> a <hi>meeting with ſome Servants of God of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Talents;</hi> apt to Teach, and forward ſo to do. When ſuch a day comes, lay up, and lock up your Spiritual Gains. <hi>Roſt what you take,</hi> as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeaks; keep, feed on it, enjoy it. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>Redeeming the time, becauſe the days are evil. John</hi> ſecond Epiſtle, verſe 8. <hi>Look to your ſelves that we loſe not thoſe things that we have wrought, but may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a full reward.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 16. <hi>Improve both of the holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> Moſt lamentably theſe are neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among us! The God of all Grace, that hath condeſcended to extremity in the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining of them, awaken Miniſters and People to better uſe of them! On God's part they are <hi>Signs</hi> and <hi>Seals,</hi> on our part they are <hi>Bonds</hi> and <hi>Badges.</hi> Baptiſm and the Lords Supper, are the utmoſt confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations God giveth us of his Promiſe to be our God; and the utmoſt we give of our Engagement to be his. Forget not this, nor vainly remember it. Plead
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:104016:19"/> with God for your Souls, his Signed, Sealed Promiſes unto you; to the expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of <hi>Diſtruſt.</hi> And plead with your Souls for God, your Sacramental Bonds given unto him, and Badges of being his put up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you; to the Conqueſt of <hi>Diſobedience.</hi> Sacramental Obligation is the chief Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe and Magazine to draw Armour from, in an Hour of Temptation. There is none like it. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.1, 2, 3. <hi>What ſhall we ſay then? ſhall we continue in ſin, that grace may abound? God forbid. How ſhall we that are dead to ſin live any longer therein? Know ye not, that ſo many of us as were Baptized into Jeſus Chriſt, were Baptized into his death?</hi> 1 Pet. 3.21. <hi>The like figure whereunto, even Baptiſm, doth alſo now ſave us, (not the putting away of the filth of the fleſh; but the anſwer of a good Conſcience toward God) by the Reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 Cor. 10.16, and 21. <hi>The Cup of Bleſſing which we bleſs, is it not the Communion of the Blood of Chriſt? The Bread which we break, is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt? Ye can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not drink the Cup of the Lord, and the Cup of Devils; ye cannot be partakers of the Lords Table, and of the Table of Devils.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 17. <hi>Hear your ſelves daily your Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſm.</hi>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:104016:20"/> I mean, the Summary of Religion, unto which you have attained. There be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſet down in my <hi>Three Queſtions Reſolved</hi> long ago Printed, I adviſe all, once a day, to go over that which they have Learned, and can Remember. Let grown Chriſtians ask and anſwer themſelves, how they do in their Hearts BELIEVE each <hi>Article</hi> of the Apoſtles Creed; how they PRAY each <hi>Petition</hi> of the Lords Prayer; how they PRACTISE each <hi>Commandment</hi> of both Tables; how they are ENCOURAGED and ENGAGED unto all three; unto the Life of Holy Faith, Prayer and Practice; I mean, by their Holy <hi>Baptiſm</hi> and the <hi>Lords Table.</hi> Rom. 2.21. <hi>Thou which teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf?</hi> Pſal. 4.4. <hi>Commune with your own Heart.</hi> Pſal. 16.7. <hi>My Reins inſtruct me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 18. <hi>Command your laſt Thoughts to be fit to be your laſt.</hi> When you compoſe you to ſleep, ſuppoſe that you may die in that ſleep. And if ſo, the God unto whom you muſt go in that death, is fit to be thought of in the entrance to it. If not, it will be ſweet in the Morning to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view laſt thoughts of him at Night. Yea, and thoſe thoughts of Faith and Love, and Truſt, at Night, will be generative
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:104016:20"/> of more of the ſame Spirit and Goodneſs in the Morning. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 63.6. I <hi>remember thee on my Bed, and meditate of thee in the Night Watches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He that in theſe things ſerveth Chriſt, is acceptable to God, and approved of Men,</hi> Rom. 14.18.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="tract">
                  <head>Motives, with Directions, unto Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Diſcourſe; ſuch as tends to promote Converſion and holy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation. By the ſame Author. <hi>Thus Publiſhed for the Poor.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE <hi>H. Spirit</hi> ſetting forth the ſin of <hi>all the Members of the Body,</hi> inſiſteth longeſt upon <hi>the Inſtruments of Speech.</hi> Rom. 3.13, 14. <hi>Their Throat is an open ſepulchre, with their Tongues they have uſed deceit, the poiſon of Aſps is under their lips: Whoſe Mouth is full of curſing and bitterneſs.</hi> He declares alſo, that our <hi>Safety depends</hi> upon the right or ill uſing hereof, <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.21. <hi>Death and Life are in the power of the Tongue, and they that love it ſhall eat the fruit thereof.</hi> And
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:104016:21"/> that one of the prime things that ſhall be <hi>brought to Judgment</hi> are our <hi>Words, Mat.</hi> 12.37. <hi>For by thy words thou ſhalt be juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and by thy words thou ſhalt be condemned.</hi> He makes our <hi>Speech</hi> the great diſcovery of our <hi>Heart, Mat.</hi> 12.34. <hi>O generation of Vipers, how can ye, being evil, ſpeak good things? For out of the abundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh.</hi> Pſal 37.30. <hi>The mouth of the righteous ſpeaketh wiſdom, and his tongue talketh of judgment.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And accordingly holy men, <hi>watch</hi> againſt the ſins of the Tongue, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 39.1. <hi>I ſaid, I will take heed to my ways, that</hi> I <hi>ſin not with my Tongue: I will keep my Mouth with a bridle, while the wicked is before me.</hi> Yea and <hi>Pray unto God</hi> to aſſiſt their watch, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 141.3. <hi>Set a Watch, O Lord, before my mouth: Keep the door of my Lips.</hi> They make conſcience of expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Image of their <hi>hearts</hi> in <hi>holy diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes,</hi> Pſal. 37.30. <hi>The mouth of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſpeaketh wiſdom, and his tongue talk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of judgment.</hi> And count it abſurd to pretend to <hi>be religious,</hi> if their <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> be not <hi>governed by Religion,</hi> Jam. 1.26. <hi>If any man among you ſeem to be religious, and bridleth not his tongue, but deceiveth his own heart, this mans Religion is vain.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:104016:21"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God,</hi> for <hi>Chriſt's</hi> ſake forgive me <hi>my</hi> treſpaſſes! And proſper unto <hi>many others, with me,</hi> theſe twelve Motives to Religious and Uſeful Diſcourſe.</p>
                  <p>M. 1. <hi>Our Speech is given us by God for Religious Diſcourſe.</hi> Jam. 3.9. <hi>Therewith we bleſs God.</hi> We do ſo, it we uſe it to the end for which He gave it. It is a <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty moſt Excellent;</hi> and therefore ought to be conſecrated unto the holy uſes, for which it was by Him <hi>intended.</hi> Otherwiſe, we oppoſe his <hi>juſt Deſign,</hi> and abuſe his rich and <hi>extraordinary Gift.</hi> That which He hath beſtown upon <hi>no Creatures,</hi> but thoſe that are <hi>capable of Religion;</hi> and beſtown it on them for <hi>no uſe ſo much</hi> as of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. 2. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is the moſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable.</hi> Doth <hi>God</hi> excel <hi>Creatures?</hi> Doth <hi>Eternal Bleſſedneſs</hi> tranſcend <hi>momentany things?</hi> As <hi>truely</hi> and <hi>plainly</hi> doth Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous diſcourſe out-ſhine <hi>all other. Men,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe <hi>Childrens</hi> talk of their Play-things; <hi>Princes,</hi> contemn <hi>Subjects</hi> talk of their Shops and Farms; and, no leſs, do <hi>New-born Souls</hi> ſlight <hi>Princes</hi> talk of Crowns and Kingdoms, in compariſon of talk concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Heaven. It is only <hi>holy Breath,</hi> that is <hi>Nobly</hi> ſpent.</p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:104016:22"/>
                  <p>M. 3. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is the moſt De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful.</hi> It is <hi>moſt apt</hi> to Delight; and <hi>doth actually</hi> Delight Men moſt, when Sin corrupts not their <hi>Senſe.</hi> As <hi>Honey</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comparably ſweeter than <hi>Whites of Eggs,</hi> when no Diſeaſe hath vitiated our <hi>Palates.</hi> For, what is Delightful, but <hi>Goodneſs?</hi> And what is Goodneſs, but <hi>Pleaſingneſs un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God?</hi> And, what Diſcourſe ſo pleaſeth God, as <hi>Religious?</hi> And who have ſo much Pleaſure <hi>as they in Heaven,</hi> who have no diſcourſe but Religious? <hi>Prov.</hi> 15.26. <hi>The words of the pure are pleaſant words.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. 4. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is the moſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable.</hi> It trafficks in the <hi>richeſt</hi> Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities. God hath no richer, than what it trades for. Yea, and its words be <hi>a wind that do always blow good</hi> unto both the <hi>Speaker</hi> and <hi>Hearer.</hi> They <hi>prevent evil</hi> Words and Thoughts abundance of them; if not much other Sin. They <hi>awaken</hi> the Speakers Mind, and <hi>affect</hi> his Heart; and give him a <hi>rich promiſe</hi> of Gods Bleſſing. Prov. 11.25. <hi>The liberal Soul ſhall be made fat: and he that watereth ſhall be watered alſo himſelf.</hi> Mal. 3.16, 17. <hi>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the Lord hearkened, and heard it; and a book of remembrance was written be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:104016:22"/> him, for them that feared the Lord, and that thought upon his Name. And they ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts, in that day when I make up my Jewels, and I will ſpare them as a man ſpareth his own Son that ſerveth him.</hi> They alſo <hi>Save</hi> and <hi>Convert</hi> ſome Souls; and <hi>Quiet</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> others of the Hearers. Talk of <hi>Health</hi> and of <hi>Riches</hi> will not cure the <hi>Sick,</hi> nor enrich the <hi>Poor.</hi> But full often hath talk of Holineſs made holy and bleſſed the Hearers of it. Who knows not many In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances?</p>
                  <p>M. 5. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is a Duty moſt Undoubted, moſt Cheap, and moſt Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tageous to do good. Undoubted;</hi> for <hi>no Law forbids any man</hi> to praiſe his God-<hi>Cheap,</hi> for what doth coſt leſs than words? or what will you ſpend for God, if you will not ſpeak for Him unto your Friends? <hi>Advantageous;</hi> for in Diſcourſe, you may better know any man's <hi>Capacity;</hi> and ſo, ſute it better, in the matter and language, than in <hi>Preaching.</hi> Beſides, you ſpeak ſingly and more particularly, and inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly. <hi>Deut.</hi> 6.7. <hi>And thou ſhalt teach them diligently unto thy Children, and ſhalt talk of them, when thou fitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:104016:23"/> when thou lyeſt down, and when thou riſeſt up.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. 6. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is a Duty of greateſt opportunity.</hi> Not <hi>a day,</hi> but Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence gives you <hi>an opportunity,</hi> for more or leſs of it. Not <hi>any Company</hi> you ever come into, but <hi>every Soul</hi> needs it. <hi>Converts,</hi> men <hi>Unconverted,</hi> and men <hi>Doubtful</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are Reconciled unto God, or no; <hi>all</hi> do need the Lips that diſperſe Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6.10. <hi>As we have therefore opportunity, let us do good unto all men, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially unto them who are of the houſhold of faith.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. 7. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is a Duty help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful unto the beſt Miniſtry.</hi> The <hi>Miniſtry</hi> has done little good upon you, until it has brought you unto the uſe of it. But when you do uſe it, you will exceedingly further the good of the Miniſtry. Some <hi>will not hear</hi> the fitteſt Miniſters for them, till Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe <hi>bring</hi> them. Others <hi>cannot Underſtand,</hi> or <hi>Remember much,</hi> till Diſcourſe <hi>help</hi> them.</p>
                  <p>M. 8. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is a Duty forced upon us by Satan's party.</hi> They are <hi>all of them, every day,</hi> ſpeaking againſt Godlineſs. How can any of the Lovers of God hold their peace, therefore? It is ſaid, that a <hi>dumb Child</hi> did once break ſilence,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:104016:23"/> when <hi>his Father</hi> was ſpoke againſt. Our <hi>heavenly Father</hi> is ſpoken againſt <hi>every day;</hi> ſhall he not <hi>every day</hi> be ſpoken for? He is <hi>every where Reviled;</hi> ſhall he not be <hi>every where Praiſed?</hi> All ſorts, <hi>young Men</hi> and <hi>Maidens, old Men</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> let their Tongues run out againſt Him; ſhall not <hi>all ſorts of his true Servants</hi> Plead for Him? <hi>O Lord, open the mouths of all, and let them ſhew forth thy Praiſe!</hi> Amen and Amen.</p>
                  <p>M. 9. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is a Duty that every good man has had the bleſſing of.</hi> I do not think <hi>any one</hi> can ſay, that all the good he ever reaped, was from <hi>ſet continued</hi> Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. Doubtleſs, all have taſted the good of <hi>familiar Diſcourſes.</hi> All muſt ſay; that <hi>gracious words,</hi> dropped from one and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother good man occaſionally, <hi>at Tables ends,</hi> and by <hi>Fire ſides,</hi> have been worth more than a little unto their Souls. And if ſo, how <hi>Unnatural is the cruelty,</hi> to ſee Souls about them periſhing, and not miniſter un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them as they themſelves were miniſtred unto? Not ſo much as dropping the words, which, <hi>by experience,</hi> they know to be helpful. <hi>Luke</hi> 24.32. <hi>And they ſaid one to another, Did not our heart burn within us, while he talked with us by the way, and while he opened to us the Scriptures?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:104016:24"/>
                  <p>M. 10. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is a Duty that is inſeparable from Charity.</hi> From the Love of <hi>God</hi> and of <hi>Men.</hi> If I <hi>Love</hi> God, I ſhall <hi>Deſire</hi> his Glory. If I <hi>rightly Deſire</hi> it, I ſhall <hi>Endeavour</hi> it. If I <hi>Endeavour</hi> it, ſurely as I have opportunity, I <hi>muſt Speak for it.</hi> If I Love Men's Souls, I cannot grudge a few words for their <hi>Converſion or Edification.</hi> Love is <hi>chill</hi> where holy Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe is <hi>ſcarce;</hi> and <hi>dead,</hi> where it is <hi>ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</hi> In all appearance dead. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>From whom the whole Body fitly joyned together, and compacted by that which every joynt ſupplieth, according to the effectual working in the meaſure of every part, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth increaſe of the body unto the edifying of it ſelf in love.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. 11. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is a Duty that is a mighty Promoter of Charity.</hi> Love, I think, is <hi>all Religion.</hi> The <hi>Soul of all.</hi> And who knows not this? Love of God is <hi>the grace we can leaſt ſpare;</hi> but <hi>the grace that of all is the moſt ſubject to abate in us.</hi> It is in us as <hi>Fire in green Wood,</hi> that needs <hi>continual</hi> blowing. And Religious Diſcourſe is an <hi>experienced Bellows</hi> to blow it. Love of one another alſo, <hi>eaſily</hi> waxeth cold. But what exciteth that, will excite this. And let Experience ſpeak; who do ſo Love
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:104016:24"/> each other, as thoſe who <hi>moſt edifie and are edified</hi> by each others Religious diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe? I can Love no Man <hi>ſo intenſely</hi> as him, who either helps me toward Heaven, or receives help from me. <hi>Philem. v.</hi> 12, and 16. <hi>Whom I have ſent again: thou therefore receive him, that is mine own bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els. Not now as a ſervant, but above a ſervant, a brother beleved, ſpecially to me, but how much more unto thee, both in the fleſh and in the Lord?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>M. 12. <hi>Religious Diſcourſe is a univerſal Miniſtry.</hi> All and every one, of Chriſt's adult Diſciples, are more or leſs <hi>Qualified</hi> for it, and <hi>Commiſſioned</hi> unto it. If thou haſt not in ſome meaſure <hi>Taſted</hi> and <hi>Seen that the Lord is good,</hi> thou art not a Chriſtian. If thou haſt, thou art <hi>able to ſay ſomewhat</hi> of that which thou haſt Seen and Taſted. And if thou haſt ſuch a Talent as that Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the exerciſe of it is thy unqueſtionable Duty. Who doubts but that our Saviour calleth <hi>all</hi> his Servants the SALT of the Earth, and the LIGHTS of the World? though one Order of them be ſo <hi>moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently.</hi> But <hi>what Salt</hi> are they, that rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly drop a ſavoury word? Or <hi>what Lights</hi> be they, who carry it ſo that no body <hi>Knows</hi> or <hi>Remembers</hi> God ever the more
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:104016:25"/> for them? Of all vile creatures, the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters that neglect Preaching, are contemned in the eyes of God and of good Men. But <hi>thus far as I ſay,</hi> you that are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> are <hi>Miniſters.</hi> And if you neglect <hi>this Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry of yours that I ſpeak of,</hi> you are more ſinful and vile than you are aware. Tell me not that there be ſome, who ſay, <hi>that it's not for Children, Women, or Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned men to talk of Religion.</hi> I know many do ſay ſo; and I know if many ſuch Sinners entice you, it will be your death to hearken, conſent, and follow them againſt God's expreſs and plain Word. <hi>Young Men</hi> and <hi>Maidens, old Men</hi> and <hi>Children</hi> are bid to praiſe God. Even CHILDREN themſelves. It is made the praiſe of the <hi>Excellent Woman, Prov.</hi> 31. that <hi>in her mouth was the Law of Kindneſs.</hi> By which, Commentators of the beſt rank do underſtand no leſs than <hi>the Law of Grace, the Word of Reconciliation, the Doctrine of the Kindneſs and Love of God towards us.</hi> Whereof this rare Matron was perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually diſcourſing with her Children and Handmaids. To conclude; Our <hi>Words</hi> have a middle place between our <hi>Thoughts</hi> and our <hi>Deeds;</hi> and of a mighty influence they are upon both; and certainly the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:104016:25"/> of them, as I have ſaid, is a great Ordinance of God for Making and Keeping good our Thoughts and Works, and our Neighbours alſo. Wherefore a needful prayer it is for us, <hi>O Lord, open our mouths!</hi> that is, give us DISCRETION wherewith to open them, and HOLY AFFECTION wherewith to open them, and deſirable OPPORTUNITIES wherein to open them for thy Glory, and our own and our Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren's Edification. <hi>Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Twelve Directions for Religious Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.5. <hi>A wiſe man will hear, and increaſe Learning.</hi> Good Proficients will give heed to firſt plain Elements.</p>
                  <p>D. 1. <hi>Underſtand well the TRUTHS and DUTIES of Religion.</hi> Read, Hear, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire, <hi>ſpare no Pains</hi> to get a good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the <hi>Creed, Lords Prayer, Ten Commandments,</hi> and Doctrine of the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</hi> A well informed mind it is, that muſt <hi>teach the Mouth,</hi> and <hi>add Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Lips.</hi> Prov. 16.23. <hi>The heart of the wiſe teacheth his mouth, and addeth learning to his lips.</hi> An <hi>inquiſitive humble</hi> man will not long be <hi>Ignorant.</hi> And when he ceaſes to be <hi>Ignorant,</hi> he will preſently be <hi>uſefully</hi> Eloquent. [And it is no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if he be not <hi>gawdily</hi> ſo]</p>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:104016:26"/>
                  <p>D. 2. <hi>Believe the things of Religion to be real.</hi> Even as the things that you ſee with your Eyes. Believe thus the Being and Glory of <hi>God,</hi> the Sinfulneſs of <hi>Sin,</hi> the Beauty and Importance of <hi>Holineſs,</hi> the Joys of <hi>Heaven,</hi> the Torments of <hi>Hell,</hi> the Eternity of <hi>Both.</hi> Whatever your <hi>Head</hi> be, if your <hi>Heart</hi> be <hi>faithleſs,</hi> your <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> will be <hi>heartleſs.</hi> And muſt be <hi>extorted</hi> from you too; it will not <hi>come freely,</hi> as little as its worth will be. But <hi>ſtrong Faith,</hi> makes <hi>forward</hi> to ſpeak, <hi>bold</hi> in ſpeaking, and <hi>unreſtrainable</hi> from it. 2 Cor. 4.13. <hi>It is written, I Believed, and therefore have I ſpoken: we alſo Believe, and therefore ſpeak.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 3. <hi>Love the real things of Religion with all your Heart. Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> too, is an <hi>idle mute,</hi> without <hi>Love.</hi> They <hi>work,</hi> yea and <hi>ſpeak</hi> alſo, <hi>by Love.</hi> It is out of <hi>nothing of the heart,</hi> ſo much as <hi>Love,</hi> that the Mouth ſpeaks. Love <hi>maketh the Lips of thoſe that are aſleep to ſpeak,</hi> Cant. 7.9. <hi>And the roof of thy mouth like the beſt wine, for my beloved, that goeth down ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, cauſing the lips of thoſe that are aſleep to ſpeak.</hi> Nothing ſooner caſts out <hi>dumb Devils.</hi> Who ever knew a <hi>great Lover</hi> of his God, a <hi>ſilenced</hi> Man? Undoubtedly our
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:104016:26"/> Affections are chilled, before our Tongues are tyed.</p>
                  <p>D. 4. <hi>Perfect the Subjection of your Selves unto Religion.</hi> Be <hi>conſtantly</hi> and <hi>uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſally</hi> under its government, in all your ways. <hi>Eat and Drink,</hi> by religious rule. <hi>Buy and Sell</hi> by the ſame. <hi>Pray and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> by the ſame. For if you allow your ſelves in any <hi>one</hi> Sin, you cannot reprove others for <hi>any.</hi> You cannot <hi>Decently,</hi> nor can you <hi>Sincerely.</hi> Under the Law the <hi>Snuffers</hi> were to be made of <hi>pure Gold.</hi> Teaching, that <hi>Reformers</hi> of other Men, were to be <hi>Unſpotted</hi> and Inoffenſive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and Praiſe-worthy. <hi>Exod</hi> 37.23. <hi>And he made his ſeven lamps, and his ſnuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and his ſnuff-diſhes of pure gold.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 5. <hi>Compaſſionate the Souls that be void of all ſound Religion.</hi> Conſider their <hi>Miſery;</hi> and their <hi>Helpleſneſs</hi> unleſs help be brought quickly. Remember that Sinners be <hi>Stray creatures,</hi> from God their <hi>Owner.</hi> And be ſinking <hi>under the burthen of their ſins,</hi> into Hells <hi>bottomleſs Pit.</hi> Remember alſo, that God who hath called thee into his <hi>way of Salvation,</hi> and hath forgiven thy <hi>Sins,</hi> will be exceeding angry, if thou <hi>hideſt thy ſelf</hi> from thy periſhing Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours. If thou <hi>Pretendeſt</hi> that thou know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:104016:27"/> not the caſe of their Souls; or <hi>Paſſeſt them by unreproved and uninſtructed,</hi> as though thou didſt not know it. God will be angry if thou ſheweſt not more Pity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on an <hi>Ox,</hi> or a <hi>Sheep,</hi> or an <hi>Aſs;</hi> yea though it be <hi>thy very Enemies.</hi> Exod. 23.4, 5. <hi>If thou meet thine enemies Ox or his Aſs going aſtray, thou ſhalt ſurely bring it back to him again. If thou ſee the Aſs of him that hateth thee, lying under his burden, and wouldeſt forbear to help him, thou ſhalt ſurely help with him.</hi> Deut. 22.1, 4. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſee thy Brothers Ox or his Sheep go aſtray, and hide thy ſelf from them: thou ſhalt in any caſe bring them again unto thy Brother. Thou ſhalt not ſee thy Brothers Aſs or his Ox fall down by the way, and hide thy ſelf from them: thou ſhalt ſurely help him to lift them up again.</hi> They be <hi>Cruel</hi> as Oſtriches, that are <hi>Dumb</hi> as Dogs. <hi>Yearn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Bowels</hi> will bring forth <hi>Edifying Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 6. <hi>Covet earneſtly your own Proficience in Religion.</hi> In the <hi>Gifts, Graces, Services,</hi> and <hi>Comforts</hi> of it. <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.25. <hi>The libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ſoul ſhall be made fat: and he that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth ſhall be watered alſo himſelf. To water others,</hi> is <hi>one</hi> way, a <hi>ſure</hi> one, and an <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to have God water us.</hi> God never <hi>muz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zles
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:104016:27"/> the Mouths</hi> of ſuch as do <hi>kindly</hi> and <hi>painfully</hi> tread out Corn to others. He doth then <hi>moſt ſenſibly Teach</hi> us, while we are Teaching others. <hi>Ordinarily</hi> he doth ſo, as <hi>Experience</hi> tells us. I believe we may <hi>all ſay,</hi> as <hi>one great man ſaith</hi> expreſly. —<hi>I am ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver backward to help or cold in helping the Souls of others, until a baſe cold is gotten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my own Soul; and it is waxed careleſs of it ſelf.</hi> Deſire of our own Spiritual good, will certainly put upon Endeavours for other Men's good. Although Covetouſneſs of earthly things puts upon a contrary practice.</p>
                  <p>D. 7. <hi>Keep a Law of Moral Kindneſs in your Lips towards Religious men, and Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>religious.</hi> Remember ſtill that Goſpel Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. <hi>Be ye courteous.</hi> Forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of it, is an <hi>extreme damage</hi> to the Intereſt of the Goſpel. It is an unknown miſchief that <hi>one rough rugged word</hi> will many times do. How many thouſands of good ones it will <hi>prevent,</hi> or <hi>fruſtrate.</hi> Whereas, <hi>Affable ones</hi> do wonderfully open our <hi>Ears, Mouths,</hi> and <hi>Hearts</hi> unto each other. Do not think to <hi>impart Wiſdom,</hi> where you do not pleaſantly <hi>expreſs Love.</hi> It muſt be your <hi>Lovers,</hi> to whom you will have much pleaſure to Diſcourſe. And who will with much pleaſure Hear you. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:104016:28"/> may you expect to <hi>make</hi> or <hi>keep</hi> many ſuch Lovers, without <hi>Moroſity</hi> and <hi>Sour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of behaviour</hi> abandoned. If Love caſt not them out, they will ſoon caſt Love out; and then <hi>farewel</hi> to good Diſcourſe. You may ſee how the <hi>very Apoſtles</hi> were fain to carry it, to maintain their Miniſtry, and its Uſefulneſs, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.7. <hi>We were GENTLE among you, even as a NURSE cheriſheth her Children.</hi> A winning <hi>Affability</hi> is as neceſſary as <hi>Breath</hi> it ſelf to profitable Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; eſpecially with weak Chriſtians.</p>
                  <p>D. 8. <hi>Perfume your own Houſes with Religious Diſcourſes.</hi> Make it ſaid in your Neighbourhoods, that <hi>happy are your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and happy your Servants which live continually near you, and hear your Wiſdom.</hi> Be ſure that your <hi>Lips diſperſe Knowledge at home;</hi> and that your <hi>Families have Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept upon Precept.</hi> Fail not to be <hi>Guides of your own Blind.</hi> Of your own <hi>Relations,</hi> of Souls under your own Roofs. Unleſs you exerciſe this <hi>Charity</hi> at home, it will juſtly enough be concluded <hi>Vain-glory,</hi> that ſets your Tongue going religiouſly abroad. And by and by you ſhall be told what is true, <hi>Prov.</hi> 26.7. <hi>The legs of the lame are not equal: ſo is a Parable in the mouth of fools.</hi> Pious ſpeeches out of a fools mouth, make the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:104016:28"/> 
                     <hi>fool</hi> ridiculous, and become <hi>themſelves</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temptible.</p>
                  <p>D. 9. <hi>By Counſel and with good Advice order your religious Diſcourſe.</hi> It is <hi>War</hi> againſt Sin and Satan, <hi>Offenſive.</hi> For Gods Glory, and Mens Salvation, <hi>Defenſive.</hi> It well <hi>deſerves</hi> good thinking; and will <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite</hi> it well. Wherefore ruſh not into it, <hi>raſhly.</hi> And do not fancy that <hi>extemporary ſuggeſtions</hi> are all you need beſtow upon it. I would that upon the walls of your houſes you had written, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24. <hi>And let us conſider one another, to provoke unto love, and to good works.</hi> The <hi>Duty</hi> required, is provocation of one another by religious Diſcourſes unto Love and good Works. The <hi>Means</hi> preſcribed, as neceſſary for its right performance; is <hi>Conſideration</hi> of one another; to wit, of one anothers <hi>Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, Conditions, Eſtates, Lives, Virtues, Faults, Wants, &amp;c.</hi> Even that we may <hi>ſuit</hi> our Miniſtrations unto them with a due heedfulneſs. And take the moſt proper <hi>Matter, Language, Method, Time,</hi> and every thing elſe to do them good. Thus do, and many ſhall ſay unto you, as <hi>David</hi> to <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gail,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.32, 33. David <hi>ſaid to</hi> Abigail, <hi>Bleſſed be the Lord God of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>which ſent thee this day to meet me. And
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:104016:29"/> bleſſed be thy advice, and bleſſed be thou which haſt kept me this day from coming to ſhed blood, and from avenging my ſelf with mine own hand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>D. 10. <hi>Let the one thing Needful, be the main one in all your religious Diſcourſe.</hi> Even RIGHTEOUSNESS; <hi>Imputed, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herent,</hi> and <hi>Practical.</hi> HOLINESS to the Lord; the <hi>Principle</hi> of it, the <hi>Practice</hi> of it, the <hi>Progreſs,</hi> and the <hi>Perſeverance.</hi> As high as they ſour in notions, &amp; in profeſſion, and in vogue, they be not the <hi>true Eagles of Heaven,</hi> that ſpend their time in catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Flies. The Kingdom of God is not in Meat and Drink;</hi> i. e. <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> conſiſts not in the <hi>Circumſtantials of Religion.</hi> Wo to them whoſe Diſcourſes conſiſt of little beſide. You ſhall not repent it, if you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine as St. <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.2. <hi>For I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined not to know any thing among you, ſave Jeſus Chriſt, and him crucified.</hi> The <hi>Converting, Edifying, Comforting</hi> Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, Crucified</hi> and <hi>Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> Doubtleſs ſo meant the Apoſtle.</p>
                  <p>D. 11. <hi>Believe Reproaches for truly reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Diſcourſes to be honours and treaſures.</hi> Otherwiſe, you will ſoon faint. But you know who thought it their <hi>Honour,</hi> to ſuffer more than Reproach. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.41, 42. <hi>And they
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:104016:29"/> departed from the preſence of the Council, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joicing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his Name. And daily in the Temple, and in every houſe, they ceaſed not to teach and preach Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> And who thought it <hi>Treaſure,</hi> even <hi>richer than</hi> Egypts. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.26. <hi>Eſteeming the reproach of Chriſt grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter riches than the treaſures in</hi> Egypt: <hi>for he had reſpect unto the recompence of the reward.</hi> Neither may you expect to reach <hi>their Heaven,</hi> if you poſſeſs not <hi>their Temper,</hi> and walk not in <hi>their way.</hi> And this remember; it is dangerous to be without ſinners <hi>Reproaches;</hi> and more dangerous to have their <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe.</hi> 'Tis <hi>its own that the World loveth.</hi> The <hi>Witneſſes of Chriſts Truth,</hi> are ſaid to have <hi>tormented them that dwelt upon the Earth;</hi> or earthly ſenſual lives <hi>Solomons Throne</hi> was ſupported by <hi>Lions;</hi> and truely ſo muſt <hi>Chriſts Kingdom</hi> and Intereſt be. <hi>Daſtardly Spirits</hi> will never be <hi>Trumpets of his praiſe;</hi> for the <hi>fear of man brings ſuch a ſnare on the heart, as tyeth the tongue it</hi> ſelf.</p>
                  <p>D. 12. <hi>Be Companions of them that beſt maintain Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Diſcourſe.</hi> With beſt <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Zeal, Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>Succeſs.</hi> Have <hi>no other Company of choice,</hi> but that which will either <hi>Teach</hi> you, or <hi>Learn</hi> from you What will be your <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> or your <hi>Patients.</hi> Let <hi>all your Delight</hi> be in theſe as the <hi>excellent ones of the Earth.</hi> And be always willing to <hi>Borrow</hi> and to <hi>Lend.</hi> To <hi>Lend</hi> to thoſe that <hi>know leſs</hi> than you do; and to <hi>Borrow</hi> from ſuch as <hi>know more</hi> than you. Otherwiſe, whatever com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany you keep, it is little, by them, that you are like to gain. For there is no Edification, where men <hi>too Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant</hi> to Teach, are <hi>too Proud</hi> to Learn: and they who have <hi>very much knowledge,</hi> have <hi>too little humility and grace</hi> to draw it forth; except it be in publick places, where they expect applauſe and acceptation with
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:104016:30"/> multitudes. <hi>Pious Humility</hi> makes us both <hi>Communica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tive</hi> of the knowledge we have, and <hi>Inquiſitive</hi> after more. And it is certain, that <hi>by communicating,</hi> the <hi>wiſeſs</hi> do grow wiſer; and <hi>by enquiring,</hi> the <hi>weakeſt</hi> do get to be wiſe. <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 10.15 <hi>The labour of the fooliſh wearieth every one of them, becauſe he knoweth not how to go to the City.</hi> The ſenſe is this, I judge: Becauſe a Fool is <hi>to proud,</hi> or too <hi>baſhful</hi> and <hi>fearful</hi> to go and enquire in <hi>the City, of one able to Direct him to diſpoſe of his Labour</hi> therefore doth he unprofitably throw it away, that it doth <hi>but Weary</hi> him and not <hi>Benefit</hi> or <hi>Enrich</hi> him (Let the Learned ſee in <hi>l. Ludov. de Dieu.</hi> in <hi>Po. Synop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
                  <p>Reader; The Serpents Seed will <hi>Hiſs,</hi> and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally againſt <hi>ſuch Arguments</hi> as thoſe, and <hi>ſuch Manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of them. I pray God they may <hi>but Hiſs,</hi> and no <hi>Sting</hi> thy Soul; for their Venom <hi>caſt on my Name,</hi> is worthy of no <hi>complaint</hi> or <hi>fear.</hi> Very probably thou wilt be told, this Diſcourſe is <hi>rankly Fanatical.</hi> Let ſuch as do ſuggeſt ſo, be told; that, godly Learned <hi>Epiſcopal Men</hi> have praiſed this Fanaticiſm. Have En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged the printing it; do buy it and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it. And Biſhop <hi>Wilkins</hi> (the late honour of his Order,) in a Sermon publiſhed by Dr. <hi>Tillotſon,</hi> (a Dean of a thouſand) hath theſe words, which are full out as <hi>Fanatical</hi> as any of mine, <q rend="inline">Practical Religion wou'd be much advantaged, if men were but more free to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wards one another in communicating their Doubts, Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, Comforts; warming their Affections, and building up one another by M<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>T<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>AL CONFERENCE.</q> O that <hi>we Diſſenters</hi> may make <hi>good</hi> uſe, and <hi>not evil,</hi> of the honour put upon us in this Nation; by Mens calling all <hi>ſerious practical</hi> CHRISTIANITY, <hi>Fanaticall Presbyterian,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
